<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Culture | Liorr Yehuda Morrison]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/categories/culture/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-10T12:54:13-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Liorr Yehuda Morrison]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meta-Learning FTW: Pairing &amp; Feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/17/meta-learning-ftw-pairing-and-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T13:51:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/17/meta-learning-ftw-pairing-and-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pair-programming is a magical thing, really &ndash; two programmers come together and achieve something they never thought possible. That&rsquo;s been my experience, anyway. Working with someone on a problem not only combines our brainpower, it also, in my experience, causes our individual brainpower to increase. When you find a good pairing partner, the experience is extremely enjoyable, fluid, and productive. You both play integral parts of the problem-solving process, throw around ideas, and ultimately solve the challenge in much less time (and with much less frustration) than if you were to go at it alone. The experience on the whole is very fun and rewarding. I&rsquo;ve had multiple experiences where, upon first looking at the challenge, I feel overwhelmed, but then a mere 30 minutes to an hour later, there I am looking at the solution to a problem I barely understood an hour earlier.</p>

<p>The only time pairing can be frustrating is if you can&rsquo;t build rapport with your partner. I&rsquo;ve never experienced this, as I always make a point to get to know the person, at the very least on a superficial level, so that it&rsquo;s not like we&rsquo;re two robots programming together. Sometimes there are situations where your pair doesn&rsquo;t communicate effectively, but if you probe them with questions, you can usually get the answer or explanation you&rsquo;re looking for. While this type of arrangement doesn&rsquo;t leave you feeling excited about pairing with that person again, per se, you don&rsquo;t get frustrated. It&rsquo;s just a less than overwhelmingly positive experience. Having said that, I&rsquo;m sure people have had negative experiences, I&rsquo;ve just been lucky not to have one yet.</p>

<p>Like pair programming, feedback is at the core of Dev Bootcamp&rsquo;s philosophy. It is an integral part of the curriculum, and we as students are required to give feedback after each pair-programming session. Overall I&rsquo;m a big fan of feedback, as it gives you the opportunity to build both your programming and people skills. My feedback has been pretty positive overall, with only some minor suggestions like, &ldquo;hey, you shouldn&rsquo;t rush through material so quickly&rdquo; or &ldquo;spend some time solidifying your grasp of Ruby.&rdquo; I would say that this feedback is generally helpful, but I think DBC students feel obliged to be more critical than they want to be. This is probably because of the fact that our feedback is rated &ndash; yes, we receive &ldquo;meta-feedback&rdquo;. The criteria for good feedback are that it is actionable, specific, and kind. I think these are good criteria, but the only gripe I have is that, if you have a nearly ideal session, sometimes you really do have nothing to complain about. But if you don&rsquo;t have any constructive criticism in your feedback, then it will score low in the &ldquo;actionable&rdquo; category. And that&rsquo;s exactly the problem &ndash; we are asked to give quantitative feedback on qualitative feedback, which is a bit paradoxical. While I benefit from giving and receiving feedback, I do not benefit from seeing how others graded my feedback. Sorry, if I have an excellent pairing session with somebody, I&rsquo;m not going to invent a criticism or force myself to be less positive just because the criteria require me to be &ldquo;actionable&rdquo;. I&rsquo;ve tried positive actionable comments like, &ldquo;keep up the good work!&rdquo; but my cohort mates don&rsquo;t seem to think that is actionable. Therefore, when I leave positive feedback, no matter how genuine it is, it will score low in the &ldquo;actionable&rdquo; category. That&rsquo;s why I don&rsquo;t put too much stock into my meta-feedback. I know for myself that I am honest and put care into the feedback I give, and if that means I am not critical, then I&rsquo;ll go ahead and take the lower &ldquo;actionable&rdquo; rating!</p>

<p>To sum up, pairing and feedback are very useful tools to guide our learning as budding developers. Although the two are linked, I would say that pairing itself is the most fruitful, while feedback is good way to make changes in order to improve future pairing sessions. The meta-feedback, while a good way to make sure people aren&rsquo;t leaving one-liners, should be more flexible and open to feedback that, rather than criticizes, simply encourages a continuation of positive behavior.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tech Issues: Gentrification &amp; the Digital Divide]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/08/tech-issues-gentrification-and-the-digital-divide/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T21:20:34-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/08/tech-issues-gentrification-and-the-digital-divide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I moved to San Francisco a couple months ago, I got a job as a driver for none other than a tech start-up whose product is very simple: deliver food from restaurants that don&rsquo;t have their own delivery drivers. I had only been in the city two weeks before starting, so I didn&rsquo;t know my way around at all. But as I raced up and down Market Street, all around the Financial District and the SoMa neighborhood, I quickly learned my way around; but that wasn&rsquo;t the only thing I learned. I couldn&rsquo;t help but notice repeating patterns &ndash; sad, disturbing patterns, really. For the vast majority of my deliveries, I would bring food to white and Asian men working in technology and finance. After breaking a sweat to find a barely-legal parking spot in these dense neighborhoods, I would encounter numerous homeless and drug-addicted people, their makeshift sleeping areas, and the pungent stench of urine. Completely surrounded by this sad reality would be the building to which I was headed, and upon entering, it felt more like a portal to a completely different world than a door to an office building. Freshly renovated offices chock-full of technology, beautiful kitchens with the latest appliances, breath-taking views, and happy, well-paid, white, male employees. Then, stepping outside again, the stench of urine is ever-present, non-white people are sitting and lying on the sidewalks with a moribund, deathly gaze, and beggars plea for even a single cent.</p>

<p>What the hell? Could the difference be any more stark? Of course a lot of factors can explain this infuriating inequality, but unfortunately the technology sector has done seemingly little to mitigate it. When I was delivering to a customer in the Mission District, I came across this powerful image:</p>

<p><img src="/images/gentrification.JPG" alt="Gentrification" /></p>

<p>It depicts several fliers posted on a house to be renovated. On the fliers, the Google bus that transports employees to the Google HQ in Mountain View from San Francisco is chasing a group of people, the symbolic image used near the border with Mexico alerting drivers that people could cross the road at any moment. These fliers speak volumes. The tech boom in San Francisco has caused a surge in gentrification, especially in neighborhoods like SoMa and the Mission District. Mark Zuckerburg himself recently bought a house in the Mission. According to <a href="http://www.newsweek.com/2014/04/25/tech-boom-forces-ruthless-gentrification-san-francisco-248135.html">a recent NewsWeek article</a>, the Silicon Valley and San Francisco tech boom has driven up evictions by 115 percent in the past year in San Francisco. Because of the city&rsquo;s inability to spread out and keep growing, people who have lived in San Francisco for decades are being forced out by young, overwhelmingly white techies who can afford to pay 2-4 times the rent the previous tenants paid. It also states that, &ldquo;Since 2011, 69 percent of the no-fault evictions have occurred within four blocks of a private bus shuttle stop for tech company employees&rdquo;. The sad thing about this is that, on paper, San Francisco is flourishing. Record-low unemployment, a strong economic base, and high median salaries paint a different picture than the one actually happening. Rather than San Franciscans getting richer, it&rsquo;s new, richer people coming into the city, replacing the less rich.</p>

<p>The technology industry is inundated with money and power. With that money and power comes responsibility, and it has fallen short of realizing and taking responsibility for the unintended consequences of its exponential growth. San Francisco has been fundamentally changed by the growth of the tech sector, and while technology brings great things, the people to make it seem to be a little too consumed with growing their businesses, their paychecks, and living a cushy life life. The conveniences that cool new apps and products bring come at the expense of people&rsquo;s very existence here in this city. It&rsquo;s not a simple problem, nor does it have a simple solution. But technology companies could start by having more outreach, having frequent employee volunteer days, for example, or investing in non-profit organizations committed to teaching the underprivileged technical stills. Instead of replacing pre-tech boom San Franciscans, they could help educate them so they, too, can stay and enjoy the city they love.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thinking Styles: Change the Way You Think]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/02/thinking-styles-change-the-way-you-think/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-02T17:55:50-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/02/thinking-styles-change-the-way-you-think</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not at all surprised to learn that my learning style is overwhelmingly &ldquo;concrete random&rdquo;, with a secondary style of &ldquo;abstract random&rdquo;. There are four learning styles, according to the Gregoric Mind Styles model:</p>

<ol>
<li>concrete sequential</li>
<li>concrete random</li>
<li>abstract sequential</li>
<li>abstract random</li>
</ol>


<p>Some tendencies of concrete random thinkers are: experimentation, risk-taking, intuiting, and independence. Concrete random thinkers benefit from trial and error; they ask lots of questions, like to jump in and try things for themselves, and are a bit competitive. These are all qualities that definitely resonate with me, and I&rsquo;m very glad to know about my learning style going into DBC. It seems the program is already set up for learners like me, as it is very hands-on, experimental, and self-directed. I will naturally engage well with the curriculum and enjoy jumping in and trying concepts out on my own. If I am struggling to understand a concept during one of the lectures, I will take solace in the fact that I will likely clear up any confusion by engaging and tinkering with the material for a couple hours.</p>

<p>Phase 0 has been very positive and overall smooth. The hardest part for me is having to learn the concepts on my own and immediately implementing them in the challenges. This was especially the case with HTML and CSS, where we had a small introduction on how to construct and style web pages, and then had to do it all on our own, to a much greater extent than the tutorial required. I&rsquo;m guessing it won&rsquo;t be the last time I have this type of experience where I am expected to go above and beyond, delving deep into a topic and learning it largely on my own. While it can be daunting to just delve into something without a route map, it ultimately leads to a profound understanding of the topic &ndash; all the frustrations and struggles help you grow, as impossible as it is to truly know that when you are in the throes of a seemingly insurmountable roadblock.</p>

<p>Working through these frustrations rather than giving up highlights one of the distinctions between the growth vs. fixed mindset. This dichotomy represents two viewpoints or mindsets regarding one&rsquo;s ability to grow and learn. The fixed mindset is characterized by a desire to seem a certain way, feelings of intense jealousy and threat upon hearing of others&#8217; successes, and avoiding challenges. Ultimately this leads to no growth in one&rsquo;s capacity to achieve something. The growth mindset is just the opposite: challenges are embraced, others&#8217; successes are inspiring, and giving up is not an option. At this point, I&rsquo;m definitely somewhere in the middle. Because I am so new to this tech world, I&rsquo;m so young, and I haven&rsquo;t finish college, I don&rsquo;t exactly have a great deal of confidence in myself; so I do unfortunately stray to the fixed mindset side of the spectrum sometimes. I get jealous and I am a little afraid of challenges. But at the very least I am aware that there is still work to be done on my mindset. I am working to actively change it, and I think DBC will provide an ideal environment for further, more substantial changes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
