<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Culture | Liorr Yehuda Morrison]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/categories/culture/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-13T15:33:24-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Liorr Yehuda Morrison]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Makes a Good Question?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/11/12/what-makes-a-good-question/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-12T13:52:27-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/11/12/what-makes-a-good-question</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hmm, good question! I would say it depends somewhat on the context in which the question is being asked, as well as the subject matter. For this blog post, to keep things within a manageable scope, I&rsquo;ll focus on what makes a good programming-related question. There&rsquo;s quite a lot of material out there about what makes good questions, and I echo many of the qualities that others have heralded. This post is a synthesis of outside sources with some of my own original thoughts and examples. The three overarching qualities that make good questions are:</p>

<ol>
<li>Specificity</li>
<li>Clarity</li>
<li>Relevance</li>
</ol>


<p>My fellow cohortmates are generally quite good at asking specific, clear, and relevant questions, but every once in a while you&rsquo;ll come across a question that more or less follows this pattern:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Help! I can&rsquo;t get this to work&rdquo;</p>

<p>(insert overly large block of code here)</p>

<p>&ldquo;Why isn&rsquo;t it working?&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>Perhaps it&rsquo;s obvious enough, but this is an example of a not-so-great question. Is it specific? No. Is it clear? Not at all. Is it relevant? Perhaps, but it&rsquo;s impossible to tell since it isn&rsquo;t specific or clear enough. You should evaluate a question&rsquo;s worthiness based on how easily you understand it, without having to run the code yourself. If anyone wanted to help out this distressed person, they would have to run the code to see what error the person is talking about, then troubleshoot it for the person. That&rsquo;s too much to ask of an answerer. Ideally, a good question is asked once the asker has already done a preliminary troubleshooting session, has isolated the problem somewhat, and asks a more specific question regarding the error message and the particular piece of code that causes the error, not the entire program. Odds are only a small fraction of the entire code file is causing the problem, so include only that code!</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s quickly look at each of the three qualities I mention are key ingredients to good questions.</p>

<h3>Specificity</h3>

<p>Is your question about a particular issue you are having with your code? Go into detail about the issue. Don&rsquo;t do what the distressed person did above and just plop the entire thing on someone else. Take time to investigate what the problem is, and explain it as specifically as you can. If you have a limited amount of characters to work with, such as in the title of a question, make sure you make it as specific as possible so potential answerers know what they&rsquo;re dealing with before they click your question. Here&rsquo;s an example of two questions, one is good and one is bad. It should be very obvious:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;How does the math module work?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;How do you endow a class with the Math module in Ruby?&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>So which one is bad? The first one, of course. It&rsquo;s not specific enough. How does it <em>&ldquo;work&rdquo;</em>? I&rsquo;m not even sure what that means, or how to answer it. It&rsquo;s far too general. And what language are you talking about? Multiple languages might have the same math module, so you better be clear about which one you&rsquo;re talking about! If your question leads answerers to ask you questions in return (like that first one), it&rsquo;s probably not good question. Now, the second one: it&rsquo;s much better. It asks about how you perform a particular action in a particular language. Anyone who stumbles upon this question in forums knows exactly how to answer it, because it is clear and specific.</p>

<h3>Clarity</h3>

<p>Make sure there are no ambiguities in your question. There should be one way of interpreting it, and it should be clear, understandable, and not too complex. Here are two more examples:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Calculating Averages in Ruby Name Error&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;I have this array: [1, 2, 3, 4] and a hash {1: &#8220;one&rdquo;, 2: &ldquo;two&rdquo;, 3: &ldquo;three&rdquo;, 4: &ldquo;four&rdquo;}. If I want to replace the array numbers with the hash variable, how would I do that?&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Which one is bad? Both of them! The first one is incomprehensible and ambiguous. It suffers from being extremely unclear and extremely unspecific. The last one, while it is specific, is still ambiguous and almost too specific to be clear. The person could have asked: &ldquo;How do you replace the elements of an array with the values of a hash in Ruby?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Again, this last question is much more digestible. It is clear, unambiguous, and specific without being overwhelming with unnecessary details.</p>

<h3>Relevance</h3>

<p>This last category is a bit trickier. Basically, an asker should ask a question that adds value to his or her understanding of a concept, and they should know their audience - who they are asking. In most cases, such as on Stack Overflow, this is a wold-wide network of brilliant programmers. Don&rsquo;t waste their time asking irrelevant or overly basic questions.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;When was Ruby invented?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;What is the difference between an integer and a float?&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>If you are seeking a fact, Google it. Why ask a team of programmers a meta-fact about Ruby that warrants, literally, a one-word response? It&rsquo;s not worth their time, and it&rsquo;s certainly not an efficient use of your time, either! And how about the second example? It&rsquo;s not quite as bad, but again, this is a very basic question that you are better off discovering for yourself through your own research. Read about what an integer is, what a float is, and try working with them. If you come across a specific problem regarding the use of integers and floats in a program, <em>that&rsquo;s</em> the time to ask a question.</p>

<p>I know I may have veered a bit into what makes a good question on the Internet, but the basic tenets still apply to questions asked in the physical world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Calm Before the Storm: Phase 0 Reflections]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/11/07/calm-before-the-storm-phase-0-reflections/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T15:33:49-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/11/07/calm-before-the-storm-phase-0-reflections</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some reflections as I finish up my penultimate week of Phase 0. This is going to be more of a Joycean, stream-of-consciousness thing rather than something with even a modicum of structure, just to warn whoever might be reading this. First of all, oh man - I can&rsquo;t believe how quickly these weeks have been passing. I think there must be a magic recipe to have time fly: just enough work and mental stimulation to keep you busy and thinking on your feet, but not enough to stress you out or overwhelm you. That is exactly what Phase 0 has been. I was challenged just enough so that I didn&rsquo;t feel bored, but not too much as to resemble the stereotyped, never-ending 9-5 work week that Americans hate but do anyway. I realize the intensive phases will not be as leisurely and balanced as Phase 0 has been, but honestly I&rsquo;m ready for a challenge. Staying at home 5 days a week, while perfectly pleasant, is not the most stimulating environment. Let&rsquo;s just say 9 weeks of Phase 0 is a good amount. Anything greater and I&rsquo;d start to get a little stir crazy.</p>

<p>Now, as for material: it&rsquo;s pretty neat to see my progress, even though it&rsquo;s not that obvious. My mind is just far more used to thinking like a programmer, and my familiarity with Ruby especially makes it so that I have many tools in my arsenal to tackle almost any logic challenge. JavaScript has been a bit of a struggle, though I am determined to overcome my aversion to it, since it seems significantly more important in the overall software development world than Ruby (client-side &amp;&amp; server-side, whereas Ruby is just server-side). This is especially true with maps and mapping software, as much of the functionality is done on the client-side&hellip; and because I am obsessed with maps, I will need to become obsessed with JS! Hmm, what else? I think after doing a fair amount of both front-end and back-end, I can say that I prefer to technical challenge of back-end stuff, though I like that, in the snap of a finger, you can see front-end changes. An ideal place for me, perhaps, would be the back-end of the front-end, if such a place exists. I want to work on things that have visual components, but I don&rsquo;t want to just be tinkering around with changing font-sizes, padding, and margin.</p>

<p>So, here I am, 9 days away from Phase 1. I look forward to delving into Ruby for the first few weeks. I am keeping in mind the cultural components of DBC and remembering that this is a kitchen and we are all cooks. I can&rsquo;t expect anything to be served to me; I expect to create and co-create and have full autonomy over what I do. I want to check in with myself every once in a while to make sure I am sticking to my goals. As I am 20 years old and without a college degree, I have so many doubts and insecurities that I will continue to try to whisk away to the best of my ability. Who would hire me? But I need to keep the faith that the status quo is changing and that, at least in the tech world, a B.A. doesn&rsquo;t mean nearly as much as an impressive technical interview or even a single cool code project. I think being in the DBC environment will really help me gain confidence, insha&#8217;Allah.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stereotype Threat: A Vicious Cycle]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/25/stereotype-threat-a-vicious-cycle/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T14:33:34-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/25/stereotype-threat-a-vicious-cycle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Broadly, stereotype threat is a situation in which a person feels themselves to be living out negative stereotypes associated with their social group. It is a vicious cycle, because as the person continues to worry about their stereotype-affirming habits or behavior, they sabotage their chances of defeating and overcoming the stereotype threat, since the concept is rooted in a person&rsquo;s perception, not in reality. As a white male who grew up middle class and attended private school all my life, I am what many people would consider the privileged of the privileged, so how on earth could I relate to stereotype threat? Honestly, I haven&rsquo;t experienced it until recently, when I joined a social group I never thought I&rsquo;d be a part of: college dropouts. Yes, that&rsquo;s right. Despite my full devotion to academic success during high school, I find myself now, a couple years after graduation, not enrolled in college. Since leaving college a year ago, I&rsquo;ve been able to keep a pretty high morale, as I have plans, ambitions, and drive; but every once in a while, it dawns on me that&hellip; I am a college dropout. I think about my friends who are still in college, studying abroad, pursuing their degrees, and here I am, not doing that. If I let myself think about this too much, I become sad, depressed, discouraged, unmotivated. It spirals out of control. Even though I am doing something far more rewarding - forging my own path, delving into computer programming - I get sad and my morale plummets. Luckily I don&rsquo;t let these periods last too long, so I&rsquo;m not actually concerned I will start to waste my life away, but it&rsquo;s still a problem I&rsquo;m dealing with.</p>

<p>As for how to combat this phenomenon, there is no easy answer. I as an individual, while not completely powerless, can only do so much to lift peoples&#8217; morales. It really is as simple as realizing that the perceived threat is not a real one - it is entirely within your power to challenge the stereotype, just say &ldquo;no&rdquo;, and life live with purpose and drive. Having said that, I realize that &rsquo;s easier said than done. It really comes down to how much confidence you have in yourself. To mitigate the effects of stereotype threat, I will try to lift people up - be complimentary, encouraging, patient. At the very least, this will help people get confidence to continue down their journeys and be less bogged down by stereotypes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meta-Learning FTW: Pairing &amp; Feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/17/meta-learning-ftw-pairing-and-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T13:51:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/17/meta-learning-ftw-pairing-and-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pair-programming is a magical thing, really &ndash; two programmers come together and achieve something they never thought possible. That&rsquo;s been my experience, anyway. Working with someone on a problem not only combines our brainpower, it also, in my experience, causes our individual brainpower to increase. When you find a good pairing partner, the experience is extremely enjoyable, fluid, and productive. You both play integral parts of the problem-solving process, throw around ideas, and ultimately solve the challenge in much less time (and with much less frustration) than if you were to go at it alone. The experience on the whole is very fun and rewarding. I&rsquo;ve had multiple experiences where, upon first looking at the challenge, I feel overwhelmed, but then a mere 30 minutes to an hour later, there I am looking at the solution to a problem I barely understood an hour earlier.</p>

<p>The only time pairing can be frustrating is if you can&rsquo;t build rapport with your partner. I&rsquo;ve never experienced this, as I always make a point to get to know the person, at the very least on a superficial level, so that it&rsquo;s not like we&rsquo;re two robots programming together. Sometimes there are situations where your pair doesn&rsquo;t communicate effectively, but if you probe them with questions, you can usually get the answer or explanation you&rsquo;re looking for. While this type of arrangement doesn&rsquo;t leave you feeling excited about pairing with that person again, per se, you don&rsquo;t get frustrated. It&rsquo;s just a less than overwhelmingly positive experience. Having said that, I&rsquo;m sure people have had negative experiences, I&rsquo;ve just been lucky not to have one yet.</p>

<p>Like pair programming, feedback is at the core of Dev Bootcamp&rsquo;s philosophy. It is an integral part of the curriculum, and we as students are required to give feedback after each pair-programming session. Overall I&rsquo;m a big fan of feedback, as it gives you the opportunity to build both your programming and people skills. My feedback has been pretty positive overall, with only some minor suggestions like, &ldquo;hey, you shouldn&rsquo;t rush through material so quickly&rdquo; or &ldquo;spend some time solidifying your grasp of Ruby.&rdquo; I would say that this feedback is generally helpful, but I think DBC students feel obliged to be more critical than they want to be. This is probably because of the fact that our feedback is rated &ndash; yes, we receive &ldquo;meta-feedback&rdquo;. The criteria for good feedback are that it is actionable, specific, and kind. I think these are good criteria, but the only gripe I have is that, if you have a nearly ideal session, sometimes you really do have nothing to complain about. But if you don&rsquo;t have any constructive criticism in your feedback, then it will score low in the &ldquo;actionable&rdquo; category. And that&rsquo;s exactly the problem &ndash; we are asked to give quantitative feedback on qualitative feedback, which is a bit paradoxical. While I benefit from giving and receiving feedback, I do not benefit from seeing how others graded my feedback. Sorry, if I have an excellent pairing session with somebody, I&rsquo;m not going to invent a criticism or force myself to be less positive just because the criteria require me to be &ldquo;actionable&rdquo;. I&rsquo;ve tried positive actionable comments like, &ldquo;keep up the good work!&rdquo; but my cohort mates don&rsquo;t seem to think that is actionable. Therefore, when I leave positive feedback, no matter how genuine it is, it will score low in the &ldquo;actionable&rdquo; category. That&rsquo;s why I don&rsquo;t put too much stock into my meta-feedback. I know for myself that I am honest and put care into the feedback I give, and if that means I am not critical, then I&rsquo;ll go ahead and take the lower &ldquo;actionable&rdquo; rating!</p>

<p>To sum up, pairing and feedback are very useful tools to guide our learning as budding developers. Although the two are linked, I would say that pairing itself is the most fruitful, while feedback is good way to make changes in order to improve future pairing sessions. The meta-feedback, while a good way to make sure people aren&rsquo;t leaving one-liners, should be more flexible and open to feedback that, rather than criticizes, simply encourages a continuation of positive behavior.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tech Issues: Gentrification &amp; the Digital Divide]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/08/tech-issues-gentrification-and-the-digital-divide/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T21:20:34-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.liorrmorrison.com/2014/10/08/tech-issues-gentrification-and-the-digital-divide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I moved to San Francisco a couple months ago, I got a job as a driver for none other than a tech start-up whose product is very simple: deliver food from restaurants that don&rsquo;t have their own delivery drivers. I had only been in the city two weeks before starting, so I didn&rsquo;t know my way around at all. But as I raced up and down Market Street, all around the Financial District and the SoMa neighborhood, I quickly learned my way around; but that wasn&rsquo;t the only thing I learned. I couldn&rsquo;t help but notice repeating patterns &ndash; sad, disturbing patterns, really. For the vast majority of my deliveries, I would bring food to white and Asian men working in technology and finance. After breaking a sweat to find a barely-legal parking spot in these dense neighborhoods, I would encounter numerous homeless and drug-addicted people, their makeshift sleeping areas, and the pungent stench of urine. Completely surrounded by this sad reality would be the building to which I was headed, and upon entering, it felt more like a portal to a completely different world than a door to an office building. Freshly renovated offices chock-full of technology, beautiful kitchens with the latest appliances, breath-taking views, and happy, well-paid, white, male employees. Then, stepping outside again, the stench of urine is ever-present, non-white people are sitting and lying on the sidewalks with a moribund, deathly gaze, and beggars plea for even a single cent.</p>

<p>What the hell? Could the difference be any more stark? Of course a lot of factors can explain this infuriating inequality, but unfortunately the technology sector has done seemingly little to mitigate it. When I was delivering to a customer in the Mission District, I came across this powerful image:</p>

<p><img src="/images/gentrification.JPG" alt="Gentrification" /></p>

<p>It depicts several fliers posted on a house to be renovated. On the fliers, the Google bus that transports employees to the Google HQ in Mountain View from San Francisco is chasing a group of people, the symbolic image used near the border with Mexico alerting drivers that people could cross the road at any moment. These fliers speak volumes. The tech boom in San Francisco has caused a surge in gentrification, especially in neighborhoods like SoMa and the Mission District. Mark Zuckerburg himself recently bought a house in the Mission. According to <a href="http://www.newsweek.com/2014/04/25/tech-boom-forces-ruthless-gentrification-san-francisco-248135.html">a recent NewsWeek article</a>, the Silicon Valley and San Francisco tech boom has driven up evictions by 115 percent in the past year in San Francisco. Because of the city&rsquo;s inability to spread out and keep growing, people who have lived in San Francisco for decades are being forced out by young, overwhelmingly white techies who can afford to pay 2-4 times the rent the previous tenants paid. It also states that, &ldquo;Since 2011, 69 percent of the no-fault evictions have occurred within four blocks of a private bus shuttle stop for tech company employees&rdquo;. The sad thing about this is that, on paper, San Francisco is flourishing. Record-low unemployment, a strong economic base, and high median salaries paint a different picture than the one actually happening. Rather than San Franciscans getting richer, it&rsquo;s new, richer people coming into the city, replacing the less rich.</p>

<p>The technology industry is inundated with money and power. With that money and power comes responsibility, and it has fallen short of realizing and taking responsibility for the unintended consequences of its exponential growth. San Francisco has been fundamentally changed by the growth of the tech sector, and while technology brings great things, the people to make it seem to be a little too consumed with growing their businesses, their paychecks, and living a cushy life life. The conveniences that cool new apps and products bring come at the expense of people&rsquo;s very existence here in this city. It&rsquo;s not a simple problem, nor does it have a simple solution. But technology companies could start by having more outreach, having frequent employee volunteer days, for example, or investing in non-profit organizations committed to teaching the underprivileged technical stills. Instead of replacing pre-tech boom San Franciscans, they could help educate them so they, too, can stay and enjoy the city they love.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
